<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A wonderful pleasant and profitable letter written by Mris Sarah Wight, to a friend, expressing the joy is to be had in God in great, deep, long, and sore afflictions. Occasioned by the death of her brother, the troubles of her mother; but especially the workings of God in her own heart. Published for the use of the afflicted.</title>
            <author>Wight, Sarah.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2106</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1681_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209156</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868045</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868045</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170255</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96467)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170255)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 210:E1681[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A wonderful pleasant and profitable letter written by Mris Sarah Wight, to a friend, expressing the joy is to be had in God in great, deep, long, and sore afflictions. Occasioned by the death of her brother, the troubles of her mother; but especially the workings of God in her own heart. Published for the use of the afflicted.</title>
                  <author>Wight, Sarah.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 81, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by James Cottrel, for Ri. Moone, at the seven Stars in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber [i.e. October] 20".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wight, Sarah --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Joy --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170255:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A Wonderful Pleaſant and Profitable LETTER Written by M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> SARAH WIGHT, To a Friend, EXPRESSING The joy is to be had in God IN Great, Deep, Long, and Sore AFFLICTIONS.</p>
            <p>Occaſioned by the Death of her Brother, the Troubles of her Mother; but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the workings of God in her own heart.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the Uſe of the AFFLICTED.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>James Cottrel,</hi> for <hi>Ri. Moone,</hi> at the ſeven Stars in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1656.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170255:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170255:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, The Lady FLEETWOOD.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> So eſteem you, upon the <hi>account,</hi> eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>God,</hi> not <hi>this World,</hi> that <hi>paſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way;</hi> I am bold to preſent this little piece, not mine own, to your view, as ſuitable (in ſome ſort) to your former, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate; having drank (in a degree) as of the ſame <hi>Cup</hi> of <hi>inward ſorrow</hi> and <hi>ſuffering,</hi> ſo likewiſe of <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>ſalvation,</hi> herein mentioned; it being the
<pb facs="tcp:170255:3"/> 
               <hi>portion of all,</hi> as ſaith the <hi>Head</hi> of all, <hi>Ye ſhall indeed drink of the Cup that I drink of.</hi> Your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhips <hi>Sympathy,</hi> together with your <hi>Dear</hi> and <hi>Noble Lord</hi>'s, with the afflicted of all ſorts, as I have largely, and <hi>multitudes</hi> of others (I believe) <hi>found,</hi> and this Author (I ſuppoſe) in particular; hath occaſioned this, preſented for a <hi>looking-Glaſs</hi> of <hi>ſolace</hi> and <hi>delight,</hi> to your <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man,</hi> by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips, humbly devoted to GOD on your behalf, <hi>R. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="apology">
            <pb facs="tcp:170255:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Some Apology to Mrs.</hi> Sarah Wight, <hi>Touching the printing of her Letter without her</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>or</hi> conſent.</head>
            <p>Choſen of <hi>God (in affliction)</hi> and precious,</p>
            <p>HAVing ſundry times read over your Letter, and found in it what my <hi>heart longed after,</hi> and in <hi>God rejoyced greatly in;</hi> I judged with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in the <hi>Light</hi> of him, the printing of it might be of exceeding uſe, eſpecially now, to the many <hi>bewilderneſſed ones,</hi> to whom it might ſerve as a <hi>VVitneſs,</hi> they having none left them (as to Man) in this <hi>cloudy</hi> and <hi>dark day,</hi> to lean upon, ſave only their dearly <hi>beloved Lord;</hi> and he neither not alwayes <hi>manifeſt,</hi> and yet <hi>manifeſt</hi> too, in a <hi>meaſure,</hi> in the true
<pb facs="tcp:170255:4"/> and alone <hi>Meſſiah</hi> in them, <hi>the Rock of Ages, and the onely Hope.</hi> This I have done without conſulting you about it, it being judged by others, (your Friends) and by me alſo, it might have prevented the publiſhing it, through a <hi>temptation</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps of <hi>modeſty</hi> in you; but thus making you <hi>publick</hi> was <hi>(I know) divinely urged of God in many,</hi> as in order to his own <hi>immortal glory</hi> and <hi>praiſe,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in your moſt <hi>moſt low eſtate;</hi> ſo to the profit and conſolation of <hi>many</hi> the <hi>like minded,</hi> but eſpecially the <hi>like af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted,</hi> (in any degree) with you; among <hi>whom,</hi> I leave you, and my ſelf with you, <hi>bowing</hi> continually (as is moſt meet) at the <hi>feet of God</hi> moſt holy, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170255:4"/>
            <head>A Wonderful Pleaſant and Profitable LETTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Recious Chriſtian friend, much beloved in the Lord of all love; in him I kindly ſalute you, wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you and your dear Relation, with my ſelf and all Saints, an heavenly increaſe of knowledge in the myſtery of our Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jeſus Chriſt: not doubting, but as ye have received ſome of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſo you enjoy daily freſh ſupplies, and at laſt ſhall be perfected in the Spirit; to the glory of God, who
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170255:5"/> hath formed you to ſhew forth his noble praiſe.</p>
            <p>Sir, in our winter-ſeaſon of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, I finde it a Chriſtians crown of rejoycing, to retire in the Spirit, to hear what God ſpeaks: for none ſpeaks or teaches like him; never man ſpake like Chriſt. In this retirement of ſpirit, or ſilent waiting upon God, we ſhall be able to ſee, and ſay with the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> that <hi>God is good of a truth,</hi> to his purified, ſincere, ſingle-hearted Iſraelites, in the midſt of all troubles; under <hi>Pharaohs</hi> bondage, at the Red-ſea, in the wilderneſs, in the firy furnace, doing them unexpected good: at all times, he is a preſent help to us, and an Ark or hiding-place for us, from all ſtorms and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts.</p>
            <p>I finde, there is no condition ſo ſad, but there is balm enough in <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead,</hi> ſutable comfort of ſupplies in <hi>Iſraels</hi> God, to revive and raiſe up a fainting ſpirit. The depths of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170255:5"/> we finde, are never beyond the depthleſs depths of mercies. When the Lord is pleaſed to make bare his holy Arm for the deliverance of his people out of troubles, he firſt lays them very lowe, that his work may be more admirable: he many times, for this very end, ſtrips us naked and bare, and deprives us of all helps and props belowe, that we may thereby learn to make the Lord alone our ſtay and truſt; who ſtiles himſelf, A God that comforteth thoſe that are caſt down, poor helpleſs nothings: this is the very time a ſoul may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect great appearances and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances from God, when its help ſtands onely in the Name of the Lord.</p>
            <p>That ſoul that findes a ſpecial pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God with it in trouble, as the children in the firy furnace, hath ample cauſe to bleſs his Name. This gracious preſence hath been much with us, in moderating the meaſure
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170255:6"/> of our croſs, though not in taking it away; which I deſire to wait the Lords time for, in praiſing him, who hath not hitherto ſuffered it to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove our ſtrength. As he moderates the meaſure, ſo the time: it's but a moment of affliction, and light, in compariſon of the greatneſs and weightineſs of the glory in eternity. O what cauſe have we to bleſs the Lord, who limits both meaſure and time, and is alſo preſent in mixing ſome comfortable Cordial, which ſweetly allays the bitterneſs of our heavie croſſes, and ſtrengthens us to bear it patiently, in ſome meaſure! As the Lord is preſent in ſanctifying a croſs; ſo when he hath perfected his noble work in us, he will be a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and perfect deliverer of us. O what a comfort is it to know we dwell in the eſpecial love of God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the croſs, as thoſe who are free from it! And though a Saint may be caſt out of a happie ſtate in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170255:6"/> world, yet never, never out of their dear God's favour. O what joy doth this adminiſter to us, to know, That however it goeth with us, yet our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will deal kindly with us, and continually accompany us with his preſence; ſeaſoning our hearts with grace, and mounting our ſpirits high, carrying them forth with pure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects to advance his glory.</p>
            <p>The true-divine ſoul, you know, is never ſatisfied, till it's as neer God as is attainable. Truly, the nearer we come to him, the more we are empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of ſin, and all ſelfiſhneſs. A Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian's happineſs lies in being empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of all ſelf, ſelf refined, as well as groſs ſelf; and in being filled with a full God, and the glorious emptying, ſatisfying incomes of his free ſpirit. Certainly, that ſoul that denies it ſelf moſt, ſeeks it ſelf moſt: for the more it endeavours to advance the Lord in all, above all enjoyments, experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, gifts, graces, relations, or any
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170255:7"/> creature, or creature-comforts; the more we exalt our condition in him. It's ſweet, and but meet, upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of any mercy, to yeeld our God all the praiſe, ſaying, Lord, as the benefit &amp; comfort ſhall be mine; ſo ſhall all the praiſes and glory be thine: Not unto me, nor unto any thing acted or done by me; but to thee be the whole glory of all, who art the author of every good and perfect gift we enjoy. It's an excellent thing, to know, own, and love the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, even in the time of adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. As proſperity ſhould not lift up, ſo adverſity ſhould not daunt a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. When we finde our eſtate here, like a web woven with intermingl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of wants and favours, croſſes and bleſſings, ſtandings and fallings, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats and victories, and the like, which hath and doth accompany a poor ſoul in its pilgrimage, as it did the Iſrael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites of old in theirs; Every condition is beautiful in its ſeaſon.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170255:7"/>
            <p> Chriſtianity hath its ſeveral Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, at ſeveral ſeaſons: it hath a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful, mourning, praying time; and its rejoycing, praiſing, triumph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing time, when it's warmed with the glorious ſunſhine of Gods favour, in which conſiſts our eternal life and joy. The ſeaſons, varieties, &amp; changes in the outward world, lively repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the ſeaſons, varieties and changes that are in the inward world of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde. I daily behold things here belowe, true according to <hi>Solomon</hi>'s deſcription; living, and dying; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the world, and going out of it; planting, and plucking up; kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and quickning; wounding, and healing; breaking down, and build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up; weeping, &amp; laughing; mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and rejoycing.</p>
            <p>I know, you, and many of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſons and daughters of <hi>Sion,</hi> can experimentally witneſs the truth of this, not onely outwardly, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly: they by an enlightned eye
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170255:8"/> behold mutability written in every thing of the firſt man <hi>Adams</hi> ſtate, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the height of his firſt glory: which glory muſt and ſhall dayly, yea doth paſs away; and will, till it ſhall ceaſe to be what it is, mixed, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. When this glory ſhall be aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, then will a more pure &amp; laſting glory diſcloſe it ſelf: the decreaſing of the one, makes clear way for the increaſing of the other. The Lord ſuffers his poore creature for a ſeaſon to take quite contrary ways, and to fetch contrary ſteps; to throw down all he builds up, and another while build up all he throws down: yea, its appointed to him to <hi>Run thorow ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny degrees of death, as he hath gone degrees of life; and to run thorow ſo many paſſages in the dark world, as he hath done in the light world;</hi> one while to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf an univerſall tranſgreſſor, and anon to juſtifie himſelf in all his tranſgreſſion; ſhewing himſelf to be as he is in all he doth as man; a fool,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170255:8"/> an unwiſe one, in all he doth; in liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, dying, planting, plucking up; in weeping and rejoycing: a fool, in making himſelf a ſinner; a Saint, till God make him <hi>what he will have him to be; this or that, here and there, when and what he pleaſeth:</hi> not what we will, but what he will, this our Potter may do with us; for we are the clay: he is our father, and we his children, at his diſpoſe; <hi>more his then our own:</hi> we are his children, I ſay, though he may withdraw from us, and becauſe of our weakneſs hide from us for a ſeaſon the true colour &amp; original of things, and thoſe various workings by which he doth thoſe things: the great Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah may put what paint he will upon things, and what Dy he pleaſeth into us: and we with beholding the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent colour ſubject to change, with the preſent eye, may be confident in what we ſee, both in judging it, and other things by it, not rightly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him that judges it, nor conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170255:9"/> what various changes both the eye and colour are ſubject to undergo.</p>
            <p>That which had a time to be born, planted and built up, hath a change accompanied to it; it hath alſo a time to die, to be plucked up, and thrown down; like the glory of old <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> or the old firſt world: and <hi>there is nothing ſo deaded, or troden under foot, plucked up, or raſed out, but ſhall have a gladſome ſeaſon, a time of quickening, glorifying, and planting, and writing in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine by the finger of God.</hi> All things are at firſt brought forth in weakneſs in the inward world, as well as in the outward world: ſaith the Wiſeman, <hi>All things under the Sun are vanity,</hi> or to have a vain courſe a while: the Lord is perfect in every motion of his, both in the inward &amp; outward world; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he doth ſhall be <hi>for ever; nothing can be added to it, or taken from it:</hi> but poor ſilly man, like the wild Aſſes colt, is weak and vain, the outward and inward man vain; yea, every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170255:9"/> of his, as he is onely man, comes to nothing, he may ſeem to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous wiſe, to have notions of great weight, even of eternity upon him; &amp; yet he cannot reach eternity as man; being but a vain empty nothing, the purpoſes he hath in him, are but poor low, ſhallow things: yet he hath his ſeaſon to take his pleaſure in his vain inventions: but when theſe ſeaſons are blown over, he is then ſtripped of all, of inſide and outſide, <hi>as I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten been;</hi> and ſo made naked to divine purpoſe. One breath of the Almighty blaſts all the creaturely perfection which we have been acquainted with; one appearance of love, diſſolves the ſoul to nothing, as the Sun doth wax: ſome boaſt, I ſee, of their ſelfiſh ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glory, Riches, honour, parts and abilities, and ſuch like; which <hi>I poor empty nothing</hi> cannot do: yet I am not troubled at it, now I conſider what a moth is in theſe garments, and how ſubject theſe treaſures are to be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170255:10"/> and creature-fulneſs exhauſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: one grain of that precious faith, and one dram of love which the Lord gives his hidden ones, is far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all other things, that we can act or do; it's all of God, without our mixtures.</p>
            <p>The Lord having ſhewn me ſome of his glory in this particular, I beſeech him to ſhew me more; for it doth content me, and it will ſuffice my ſoul more then hid treaſures: the ſenſible and full enjoyment of thy Spirit, will cauſe my ſoul to return ſatisfied to her reſt, praiſing the God of all our mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; not caring what others boaſt of, when thou art become the Crown of my glory, the top of all Royalties to me; my ſpirit now breaths out this language, &amp; ſays, Holy God, let who will treaſure up to themſelves, yet will not I: that which ſome love and ſtore up beſides thy ſelf, of their own excellency; I cannot but abhor, &amp; caſt away, as filthy raggs of no value: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170255:10"/> thing that is in me, that ſprings up out of my dry ground, that ſprings not from the ſap of thy Holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>If I know my own heart, I would not glory in any thing below my Maker, and what is of him, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed by his Spirit alone into me: it rejoyceth my ſoul much, to ſee the Lord at work, gathering all, as he hath given me as his own, and ſaving me for his own Name ſake, and not for any worth, or worthyneſs in me, Juſtifying me, or any unworthyneſs condemning me: O how admirable is it for to find God thus freely and fully loving and ſaving his poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and owning all that is his, as he hath been and appeared in them; and cauſing all that hath been and ſprung from us to paſs away for evermore: My ſoul ſhouts forth with the true ſpiritualized Chriſtian, this voice: Dear God, as I am a ſelfiſh corrupt creature, ſo let there be no profit of all my labor and travel; but thou who
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170255:11"/> alone art the Author of every good and perfect gift we enjoy, do thou reap the travels of thy ſoul, <hi>for its high time for thee to enjoy thy own:</hi> for my part, I cannot but turne from all the fruitleſs works of my hands, all the motions and delights of my Spirit, in the inward world of my heart, and with as much irkſomneſs and great tiredneſs of ſpirit, as ever <hi>Solomon</hi> did in the outward world: yet I know every thing is beautiful in its ſeaſon, time and place, though nothing is lovely out of it: there is a beauty in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, when the ſpring of life is come: O how lovely is it! thee is alſo a beauty in death, when that ſeaſon is come: it's as beautyful to ſee things in Winter, as to ſee them live in the Spring of Summer: there is nothing ſo deformed, but, when we look upon God in it, we ſee much beauty written in it; nor nothing ſo evil, but it hath good on it: there is nothing ſo bad, but it's good in its own order, place,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170255:11"/> and ſeaſon, and courſe; nor nothing ſo good, but it's bad and uncomely out of its place, order, and ſeaſon. There is a beauty in killing, healing, weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; in Rejoycing, and triumphing: but this beauty ſhines not ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous out of their ſeaſons, as it doth in: <hi>There is the very nature and exellency of God in every thing that he doth;</hi> which makes it beautyful: for every thing that ſprings from him, ſavours and taſtes of his life and perfection.</p>
            <p>The outward and inward man hath but a poor, lowe, dark, ſhallow know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the things of God, whatever they may pretend to have. There is no ſoul able of it ſelf to reach theſe things; they are onely ſpiritually diſcerned, and known by the ſight of the Spirit: it's by this Spirit onely, that the ſoul comes to know, obſerve, and underſtand the ways and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of God in the deeps, and his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious motions and operations in things which he doth. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170255:12"/> ſeen in the Root by the ſenſe of the creature, as it lies or ſprings from thence, or as it returns thither. Man, as man, you know, hath onely a bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh underſtanding of every thing; ſo of God: <hi>I had not</hi> (ſays one) <hi>the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of a Beast,</hi> as of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſo of all his motions, thoughts, actions and intentions, in and about things, times, places and perſons; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely a preſent appearance of this or that, not knowing what it is, whence it came, what it means, or whither it tends. So he judges ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to a preſent outward appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and ſhews himſelf to be what he is, and what God will have him to be, A fool in himſelf, that the pride of his glory may be ſtained, and God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone exalted.</p>
            <p>Though this be a dark obſcure diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, yet becauſe God will have it ſo with us, this is beautiful in its ſeaſon: as darkneſs is proper for the natural night, ſo is ſpiritual darkneſs
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170255:12"/> for the ſpiritual night as proper for it: as light becomes the day, and as truth and ſubſtance is proper for it; ſo are ſhadows and lyes for the night: &amp; while the night remains, it's as ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table they ſhould remain, as when the day dawns the ſhadows fly away: O how clearly doth herein the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Chriſt, of <hi>Sion,</hi> the holy ſeed, appear! though they are not exempted from any varieties or changes in the inward or outward world running thorow them; yet they ſtill ſweetly remain the ſame: being one with the Father, they are as he is; like him, as <hi>Seth</hi> was like <hi>Adam:</hi> what ever their cloathes, their appearances be; yet their life and ſubſtance is ſtill the ſame. For a ſeaſon, the inward man I find, is ſo benighted, and bewilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, yea all his life ſo deaded, and his light ſo put out, and his glory darken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that he is made to ſee and confeſs, that he knoweth nothing as he ought to know, nor hath nothing to boaſt of,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170255:13"/> no more then the outward man; and that it's onely the ſpiritual man that ſhall grow up to perfection, and live and flouriſh, whether in the ſeed, or grown up.</p>
            <p>For the coming of this full enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all bleſſedneſs &amp; happineſs, longeth my poor waiting ſoul, in a daily expectation, upon the God of all our mercies, who is coming to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill our deſires, to compleat our glory: he comes not with a thought to tarry or go back; he comes ſwiftly with ſpeed, leaping to meet his beloved waiting <hi>Jacobs,</hi> to revive their ſpirits with his loves, his wiſdom, power, grace, goodneſs, yea all his Riches of grace and glory; that they may ſing ſweetly, ſtrongly, thorowly, fervent, and frequent, the new ſongs of <hi>Hoſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Hallelujahs,</hi> bleſſing and glory, power and praiſe to our God for ever, who is the Authour of all our preſent good, and the <hi>Omega</hi> of our perfect happineſs, in that heaven of heavens
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170255:13"/> where Juſt men made perfect take up Sanctuary and aſſured Reſt for ever, ſolacing their ſouls with their Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veds loves; the riches, honors, pleaſures and ſoul-delights of eternity that are in the boſome of our dear and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous father: in the full fruition of this reſt and glory, longeth my waiting ſoul to be, where time ſhall be no more; the time of ſin, ſorrow, paine, death, any weakneſs or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection: when that which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect is come, I know all this which is imperfect will be done away: yea then there will be no complaining or cauſe of complaining within or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, becauſe all ſin, and ſo all ſorrow and ſighing ſhall certainly be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, as being momentary; &amp; the pure language, the new melodious tune of Joy and gladneſs from the Spirit, ſhall be onely ſung, heard, and known to be for ever in the Saints, to their Saviour, who is our choice, our chief, our only and dearly beloved One in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170255:14"/> all, without and above all in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>Worthy Sir, becauſe Honourable in the Lambs cloathing, having put pen to paper with an intent to ſalute you &amp; your neer relation with a few broken fragments gathered up from my Maſters table, I ſhall take leave, having a little freedom, to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate a few more lines to you; hoping it will not be too burdenſome to you. Sir, I cannot but Chriſtian-like thank you for your Remembrances of us at all times; though I know you are in covenant with that God, who will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence ſevenfold into your boſom, for all your labor of undeſerved, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected love: your ſympathizing, from a fellow-feeling of our afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and others, plainly demonſtrate you to be a fellow-member of that myſticall body whereof Chriſt is the Head: O what a mercy is it to be heartily affected with the afflicted! to have the ſame mind which was in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170255:14"/> Chriſt in us! to have the ſame love one to another, as Chriſt hath to us, in quality, though not in quantity! The love of the Lord in his people, is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times made out to them in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected way, to wonderment, when they think leaſt of it: as <hi>Hagar</hi> ſaid, the Lord looked after her, when ſhe looked not after him; ſo doth he to many of his people oftentimes, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide and protect them in a way and manner which they cannot but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and bleſs his Name. It's a wonder to mee ſometimes, to ſee how ſenſible one Chriſtian is of anothers ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>becauſe it's ſo rare:</hi> but when I conſider that all the Saints have but one God, one Father, one Faith, one Baptiſme, one Love, one Spirit, who dwells in them all, and runs thorow them all, and conveys it ſelf to all as it pleaſeth, whether abſent or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, afar off or neer at hand, known or unknown by face: Although the Saints are ſcattered abroad in this
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170255:15"/> wide, wilde world, and diſtinct in the fleſh from one another; yet are they one in the Lord, and ſo love, ſympathize, ſorrow, and rejoyce toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as members in truth of Chriſts body: Chriſt was of a ſympathizing ſuffering Spirit; and ſuch hearts, qualities, and diſpoſitions, he would that we ſhould have: therefore he puts his Law of love and kindneſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us: <hi>he takes our humane nature, and infuſes his divine nature into us:</hi> Chriſt bears all our griefs, and carries our ſorrows, and in all our afflictions is afflicted with us, and for us.</p>
            <p>O how good is it, in our wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of trouble, to lean upon this our Beloved, who can bring us out of them all! we are very apt to ſtumble at the way and maner of Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations, when we have little cauſe for it, if we did but conſider that he hath glorious ends in all he doth and ſuffers, for the exaltation of his Name and our ſole comfort<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:170255:15"/>
            <p> Though the Lord may croſs his people in the way of his providence, ſo that all things may fall <hi>alike to all in this World before men;</hi> yet not in his account hereafter: for he may give us to look unto him in his word of Promiſe, and there behold him by an enlightned eye, doing all things after the counſel of his own good will and pleaſure, for his glory, and our ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting comfort, beyond and above all outward ſenſe and external hopes; as he did to <hi>Abraham,</hi> calling things that are not, as though they were: <hi>I am not ſo much a worder, as an admirer, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle writer of the wonders of God in the deep of affliction;</hi> to ſome of my fellow-ſufferers, who have been bewildered in their ſpirits as I have been, though now through rich mercy in ſom mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure refreſhed with the crums of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naans</hi> comfort, &amp; drops of honey and milk, grace and love, that flows from our good ſpiritual land. Much of Gods fatherly Dealings, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhings,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170255:16"/> I might relate unto you, which my hungry, thirſty weary Reſtleſſe ſoul hath known, ſeen, and felt, in the day of trouble, the hour of ſad temptations, if I had freedom.</p>
            <p>Sir, the ſharp exerciſe which hath been upon my ſpirit, ſince that little unknown book was made, of Gods glorious Diſplayings of light and love upon a poor, dark, forlorn, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing-creature in an unexpected time, I was not then capable of the publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it: if I had, I could not be free, fearing how it might be with me af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards. Truly, ſince then, I have had a ſharp Winter-ſeaſon, mourning for the loſs of all that comfort: I have been ſtripp'd ſo bare of ſeeming com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ſince, that I cannot boaſt of that, nor of any comforts, <hi>but of the God of comforts;</hi> not of enjoyments, or expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riences; not of any gifts or graces; <hi>but of the giver alone, and of my infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;</hi> and in that Power of Chriſt which hereby is made more manifeſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170255:16"/> in us: <hi>the Lord alone is the boaſt and glory of his people;</hi> in his Name we ſet up our Banners, and upon him alone ſhall our mind be fixed, and our ſoul-affections ſet, and not on things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: this is to have our hearts above, on things remaining; not ſhadowy, but ſubſtance; and our converſation in heaven, though we tabernacle in houſes of clay in the world. When Chriſt is our only object, then, but not till then, will all below be our abject, in compariſon of a full God, a naked Chriſt, a free Spirit. O that it might be all our aimes and ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to take up our croſſes and follow Chriſt fully; even thorow fire and water: for here our God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to be with his people; and when we are <hi>purged and purified enough he will lead us out into a wealthy place, of peace and Joy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O that we could walk in our Maſters ſteps without ſtumbling, and do as he did, run our race with joy; knowing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170255:17"/> if we run, we ſhall obtaine the Crown, which is not to be had on this ſide the end of it: Surely this prize is worth the running, waiting for, and longing after, till we enjoy it. Our ſuffering and Croſs is but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while, for a ſmall moment; but our glory is for everlaſting, our reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ever. Thrice-happy is that ſoul, whom God <hi>chuſeth for his own in his furnace,</hi> and <hi>chastens in his ſchool:</hi> happy entering, happy in it, and for ever happy afterward. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs and Happyneſs is annexed to Gods chaſtning: Bleſſed and happy is the man God correcteth, and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth new leſſons thereby: therefore not to be deſpiſed: Our loving Father, even <hi>ſmiles,</hi> when we <hi>think</hi> he <hi>frowns upon us:</hi> when he <hi>ſeems to strike us, he stroaks us.</hi> He doth to us, ſometimes, as he did to <hi>Adam,</hi> convey a precious promiſe, with a ſad threatning; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>The ſeed of the woman, &amp;c.</hi> Mercies oftentimes come veiled to us; and a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170255:17"/> ſentence of death may paſs upon our choiceſt mercies, as did upon <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> for the tryall of our graces; which would not ſhine ſo bright, if not fire-tryed, with <hi>Abrahams;</hi> whoſe faith, love, and holy obedience to God, after thus tryed, ſhined more eminent and glorious.</p>
            <p>I find our ſad viſitation known to you, Sir, was not ſo much a Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as ſome may call it; but rather a ſtrict tryal, to try our faith, love, patience, and pure good-will to God; whether it be ſimply and entirely to him, without by-ends, as Satan would have accuſed <hi>Job</hi> to God, ſaying, <hi>Doth Job love,</hi> or ſerve <hi>God for nothing?</hi> &amp; alſo to try our ſtrength, what we can do or ſuffer for God; and alſo to try our wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, how prudent &amp; patient we could behave our ſelves like true Chriſtians, in the loſs of all outward enjoyments, though deare and precious to us; not onely in fleſh, but in Spirit.</p>
            <p>O what an unſpeakable mercy is it,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170255:18"/> to finde and feel God enabling of us to hold out in theſe firy tryals! ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well of the Name of our dear God, owning him in giving mercies to us, and not friends; and owning him to take them from us, and not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: the Lord gives &amp; takes alſo. Truly the Lords tryall in theſe things, is a firy ſtrict tryall: God tries our Faith and love, as he did <hi>Abrahams,</hi> by cauſing him to offer up his onely ſon <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the ſon of promiſe: <hi>Now I know,</hi> ſaid God to him, <hi>in doing this, that thou loveſt me:</hi> and thou ſhalt know it; for <hi>in Bleſsing I will multiply Bleſsings upon thee and thy ſeed;</hi> This aſcending ſpark of love in <hi>Abraham,</hi> from God to God, did as I may ſay engage the Lord to deſcend ſhowers of bleſſings upon him, and his ſeed. Our God in wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom doth all things: he tries and proves us, to do us unexpected good in the latter end: he tries whether we can live in the practicall part of Chriſtianity, what we can do and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170255:18"/> ſuffer in truth for Chriſt; whether we can be content to leave all for him; be content with Chriſt alone, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out freinds, or the world, gifts, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, qualities, and conditions, and ſuch-like in one hand, and Chriſt in the other; <hi>whether we can be content to reſign up all to God, all outward, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, things; all Relations, Ordinances, Gifts, Graces, Deſires, Hopes, all that can be named or deſired of Heaven and Earth; that nothing of ſelf may Remain;</hi> none of our wills, deſires, ends, hopes, but all croſſed and deſtroyed in us, which is contrary to the Lords will: the Creatures will being ſo contrary to Gods will in all things, it's well to have it croſſed, though it be in that which may be moſt for its ſeeming comfort. Surely they who are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the excellency of Gods hidden Divine will, would not have it croſſed, but rather its own will in any thing, though it may ſeem hurtful to it; ſure it's thus.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170255:19"/>
            <p> Sir, I ſhall acquaint you a little what a hard thing it was for me to ſubmit to this will of God, though ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to him to make me quietly ſubmit, and reſign up all to him, in the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of my dear Brother. Though the diſpenſation was dark and diſmall, <hi>yet I dare ſay from a full perſwaſion, after many doubts, that though it might ſeem in Judgment, yet God hath received him to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting mercy: for being weak, I finde he was ſuddenly overcome by the strong man, not willingly, but by conſtraint; mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with many unnamed inward and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward fears and troubles. Certainly, what is not done in deſpite, willingly, againſt God, but the violent hurrying of Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, through weakneſs, not willingly, ſhall never be layed to any poor tempted ſouls charge.</hi> The Lord doth not look ſo much to the weakneſs of his creature, and temptation, as to his own rich mercy and free love. Surely thus the God of love hath looked upon my dear departed Brother; for I had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170255:19"/> of him in his life-time, that when he was himſelf, he <hi>ſerved the Lord with many Tears, and Temptations oftentimes;</hi> and did endeavour to walk as exact as a Chriſtian, to that light of knowledg God was pleaſed to meaſure out to him. Much I might ſay of this nature, had I oportunity, and thought it convenient: which cauſeth me to <hi>Believe the Lord hath not looked upon him to take advantage of his weakneſs, to destroy; but to ſave him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the multitude of his tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; and being a God of love, patience and long Suffering, hath, I am now perſwaded, though one while I was much troubled with doubts and feares, hath taken him from ſin and ſorrow, to bliſs and bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: He was of a very weak Constituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of body.</hi> Truly, dear friend, the great loſs of ſuch a comfortable ſtaff, ſuch a hopefull ſon, and brother, the maner and unexpectedneſs of his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from us, hath been a ſword in our bones, firſt pierced thorow our ſoul;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170255:20"/> which hath cut us to the heart: Firſt, from a ſerious conſideration of Gods diſhonour, by opening the mouths of the ungodly, to cauſe them to ſtumble at the way of God, ſaying, What profit is it to ſerve God? and are theſe they that made the Lord their truſt? and ſuch-like things. And ſecondly, the Saints diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, beſides our own great diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in the middle of our ſuppoſed comfort. I hope the effect of the ſword I mention, will prove the Lords ſevering ſword, to ſeparate more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween fleſh and Spirit, Chriſt and the creature.</p>
            <p>I find, all that God doth, is to try us whether we can love God as well in the way of his Judgments, as in the way of his mercies; love him in caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us down, as raiſing us up: in ſmiting as healing, in Winter as Summer, for all, in all changes and conditions, above all: many are the troubles of the holy ſeed of God; and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170255:20"/> truly <hi>did we not ſuffer ſomething, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining part of Christs ſufferings would be unfulfilled; which tryal and proof he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures in us:</hi> as he ſuffered in the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, ſo we in truth: O there is a neceſſity of our ſuffering ſomething, if we would be feelingly ſenſible of what Chriſt hath ſuffered in the fleſh for us, to crown us with glory in the Spirit, and be ſympathizing with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in affliction, and really magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying that free grace of God which ends in full glory; cauſing us always to extol the Lord, bleſſing him with a triumphant ſong of praiſe. I am ſure the Saints have cauſe to bleſs the Lord at all times, even in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, becauſe this is the place where God uſually ſpeaks comfortably to his people. Though he lead them this ſolitary way, yet it's the right way; <hi>the way of the Lord is an unknown ſtrange way, even in the whirlwind.</hi> O what a happyneſs is it to finde, afflictions come not out of the duſt, but as we
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170255:21"/> may ſay, they are the finger, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, for our good: he makes them antidotes to us, to expell poyſon: the more we have of them Sanctified to us, the more pure, like Chriſt: we have no cauſe to ſay when we are under the rod, therefore not beloved of our Father, becauſe ſo and ſo afflicted; but the rather loved of our Father, becauſe chaſtned: here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are made more conformable to Chriſt, by being buried with him in the Baptiſme of his ſufferings: The Cup of affliction, which the ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ones drink of, is a Fathers Cup; which they cannot but drink, hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them for their good from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; whoſe ways are all mercy and truth, whoſe paths drop fatneſs, whoſe out-goings and in-comings are all ſweet and precious to us. The poor creature in trouble, is very apt to cry out and ſay, Is this and this a pleaſant way? is this a comfortable condition? and can God indeed bring
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170255:21"/> good out of ſuch great evills? O it's impoſſible.</p>
            <p>Thus I have thought often: Can any good come out of ſinfull <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,</hi> out of my confuſion, and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? O it's impoſſible: with us it is, but not with God, who at firſt commanded light to ſhine out of darkneſs. O what cauſe have we to exalt Gods power and love in the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry furnace! to glorifie him in the fires, is moſt excellent: O they cannot but do it, when they ſee him keep them alive in the midſt of that fire which conſumes onely the droſs, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Gold pure for his Uſe: <hi>That enlightening hony which is in the top of our Gods Rod,</hi> doth enlighten us to behold this great and glorious ſight, why the Buſh burns, and is not conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. O this honey out of the rock, Gods love-manifeſtations, will ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, and doth, all conditions and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to us and all Chriſtians. ſome are afflicted for the tryall of faith
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170255:22"/> and patience, that they may have their perfect work by exerciſe. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, that the handy-work of God may be made more manifeſt upon us, the Lord may take away our corn, Wine, Wool, and Oile which he giveth us, when we do not prize him above all; that hereby we may learn to love our giver more then gifts, and to know the worth and ſweetneſs of them more by the want of them a while: We may be <hi>Deprived of any comforts, yet not of the God of comforts;</hi> and ſadly caſt down, yea ſeemingly forſaken, and overwhelmed with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows like unto <hi>David,</hi> and weary of life with <hi>Job,</hi> diſtracted as <hi>Heman,</hi> and yet belong to, and dearly beloved of God, as they were: therefore it's good to take up this Holy Reſolution, to wait on God in the way of his ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Judgments, and in meditation of his loving-kindneſs, till he ſhall make hard things eaſy, and crooked things ſtrait, rough places plain, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170255:22"/> bring to light the hidden things of darkneſs, making darkneſs light be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us. Said good <hi>Jacob,</hi> (who found it good to wait upon God) <hi>I have waited for thy Salvation;</hi> and I will wait: and <hi>David, In waiting I waited:</hi> and <hi>Job, All my appointed time will I wait till my change come.</hi> O how deſirable a thing is it to ſee Chriſtians have ſuch patient, believing, ſubmitting hearts to the Lords will: <hi>Though he kill me, yet will I trust in him:</hi> and, <hi>I am thine, ſave me:</hi> This is a ſweet rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on God in a day of trouble; and ſaying with Chriſt, <hi>The Cup which my Father hath given me, ſhall I not drink it?</hi> it's a Cup, not a Sea; and a Fathers Cup, not an enemies; and a Fathers gift.</p>
            <p>By conſidering theſe things, the Lord pleaſed to work comfort, renew his love to my ſoul when much troubled at my deare brothers death, by which I hope the Lord will gradually cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie all that he would have crucified,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170255:23"/> and blaſt all of creature-props and helps, that he alone may be our one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtay and bleſſedneſs. The neerer a ſoul comes to God its haven of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, the more it meets with ſad ſtorms and tempeſts: Which makes our port of glory more deſired, and gladſome to us when we come unto it: <hi>The bitterneſs of miſery ſets off the ſweetneſs of mercy, as the blackneſs of the night the glory of the day:</hi> I am ſure my brothers afflictions here, were ſharp before he went hence; which cauſeth me to believe he is now for ever comforted: Some comfort came from this word to me; Refrain thy voice from weeping, and thy eyes from tears, when my ſoul was in bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs; for thy work ſhall be reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Lord, and thou ſhalt <hi>ſee him again with greater Joy:</hi> though thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire was croſſed here in ſome things, as <hi>Davids</hi> was and others; <hi>Yet ye ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce together in my Kingdom. I finde this was of God coming in power to the</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170255:23"/> 
               <hi>ſatisfying of my troubled ſoul in an agony of ſorrow. I anſwered this voyce, Lord, it's enough if thou make thy word good: thy will, thy unknown will, by any but thy ſelf be done, O Father.</hi> And further it was ſaid, That nothing ſhould ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate him and Chriſt, nor eſtrange his love from him.</p>
            <p>Till God appeared in this maner to me, Quieting my heart in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, I was much troubled touching his honour, to think how he would ſuffer by ſome, till he told me he knew what was moſt for his glory, far better <hi>then ſilly I.</hi> Truly I may ſay, How had it been unleſs the Lord had been on our ſide! wee had almoſt fainted, and dwelt in ſilence; had not Jehovah our Mighty God been ſeen in the mount wonderfully for our preſervation and deliverance; for which I deſire to Bleſs his Name for ever, who comforts me much from theſe words, bidding me look to <hi>Jeſus</hi> the Authour and finiſher of our
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170255:24"/> Faith, who for the Joy that was ſet before him, endured the croſs, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed the ſhame, and is now ſet down on the Right hand of the Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty on High. He was oppreſſed and afflicted, yet he open'd not his mouth; learn of him, for he is meek and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which makes him ſo unſpeakable lovely. Patient was Chriſt when he ſuffered: <hi>he overcame by patience, as well as by power.</hi> As Chriſt was patient, ſo was his members; and ſo ſhould they be like <hi>David</hi> in their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering ſeaſons: ſays <hi>David,</hi> I was dumbe, and opened not my mouth: and let the Righteous ſmite me, and it ſhall be an excellent Oil; it will be for my profit; his correction.</p>
            <p>This our loving friend, Chriſt, will not wound us, but heale us; when he ſmites, he ſmiles upon us: for he even then refreſhes us with his brook, and well-ſpring of life, in our wayleſſe wilderneſſe, under all our ſorrows and ſmitings; and hereby
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170255:24"/> God makes us to lift up our heads with Joy and praiſe. O what cauſe have We to bleſſe the Lord under our croſſes, for his ſupporting hand of love! truly, as great cauſe, as if he took them away from us. It's a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable thing to own God to be Juſt, when he ſhews mercy; and when he gives grace, to be ſtill exalting the Riches of his glory. O the happy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the heavenlyneſs of thoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualized ſouls, whoſe wills are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued to the Lords will in all things; ſo to acknowledge him Righteous in all he doth, and our ſelves vile! O what a bleſſed ſtate are they in, who have no will to be guided by, but the Fathers will in all things; which ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily learns them to deny and defie ſelf fully, in all they do and ſay; and to eſteem onely of God and the workings of his Spirit above all. O that we might be as Chriſt was, love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in all conditions, by our Holy ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to our Father! Chriſt we
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170255:25"/> know learn'd obedience by the things which he ſuffered. O how lovely was he when he lay in a Manger, when he lay on the ground, and ſweat Water and Blood; when he was ſcourged, and crowned with Thorns; when he hung on the Croſs between two Theeves; when he lay in the grave! even now Chriſt appeared moſt lovely, by how much he abaſed himſelf thus low. O how deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a thing is it to ſee goodneſs and greatneſs kiſs each other in one noble perſon! O what a great condeſcention of love was this in ſuch agreat perſon as Chriſt, who is King of Kings! O that ſuch a gloryous Majeſty ſhould ſo low condeſcend to ſuch poor, weak unworthy worms, to teach ſinners in his way, to doe as he hath done, to ſuffer patiently and willingly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt gainſaying or reſiſtance, ſuch grievous things! Chriſt was as a ſheep before the ſlaughter: <hi>David</hi> under afflictions was dumbe alſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170255:25"/> he ſaw the Lord did it, and not man: ſo <hi>Aaron</hi> when he loſt his ſons ſuddenly, held his peace: And good old <hi>Eli</hi> ſaid, It's the Lord, let him do as he pleaſeth. In this ſweet ſpiritual frame was <hi>Job,</hi> when he ſaid it was the Lord that took from him in the fleſh, who could give him much more in the Spirit. All that they ſuffered, was not ſo much from an enemy as a Father, for their good; who ſeeing how apt the current of their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons was to run more to them then to him, their heart being not ſo fixed upon him as he would have them, but very apt to be divided, and to wander from him, like ours as we are creatures; therefore he ſends afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as meſſengers to fetch them home to his Sheepfold.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Once this word came in Power to me when I was very ſad: O ſoul, grieve not, grieve not for thy Brother: precious in my ſight is thy Brothers death, though griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to thee and others: was not Christs</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:170255:26"/> 
               <hi>ſufferings much more terrible? and think not ſtrange your firy tryalls; for what is befallen you, is common to all in this life: and the ſame afflictions are accompanied to your fellow-members in the world. Think of Samſons death, a good man, who died among the Philiſtins, and ſeemingly in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be revenged on them for his two eys. Conſider theſe things, and lay them to heart; and ſorrow no more as one without hope; but know, all things ſhall worke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather for good, even this, unto ye: therefore be ſtill, and know I am God, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whatever I pleaſe, in heaven, and earth, and all places: his time was not in thy hands, or friends, or his own, but in my hands: A ſparrow cannot fall to the ground, nor a hair off the head, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my knowledge.</hi> When theſe things was ſpoken to me, I was very reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in my ſpirit, even reſolving to ſpend my few days in <hi>ſilent ſorrow,</hi> not expecting any more Sun-ſhine days of joy: and <hi>ſuddenly</hi> the <hi>glory of the Lord broke forth thorow ſome thick</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170255:26"/> 
               <hi>darkneſs, bidding me lift up my head; and the Lord was pleaſed to ſpeak to me as ſweet as ever; telling me he would wipe all teares from my eyes, and the rebuke or reproach of his people he would take from off all the earth: he had ſpoken it who would do it, Jehovah, a fulfiller of Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: therefore let not thy troubled fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart be diſquieted or afraid: Peace, Peace be unto thee.</hi> I found Chriſt reaſoned with me, as once he did with his diſciples when they were ſad; <hi>Why are ye troubled? and why do ſuch fears and doubts ariſe in thy heart? am not I and my favour more to thee, then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments or Relations, or any thing thou canſt deſire? though I chasten thee ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to draw thee neer me; yet my favour will I not take from you, nor alter my love: is not this, O ſoul, more then all, to give thee my ſelf, Who am the Deſire of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, the Beauty of all Bleſſedneſs, the top of all Royalties; even the fulneſs that ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth all in all; who hath made thee beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thorow my comlyneſs: though black</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:170255:27"/> 
               <hi>in thy ſelf under the bondage of coruption, yet Lovely as Redeemed, Juſtified, and Sanctified?</hi> my ſoul was even melted with in me, at this ſweet and powerful manifeſtation of love, that I cryed out, None but <hi>a naked Chriſt:</hi> and who would not ſell all, for this <hi>Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pearl,</hi> and willingly reſigne up all even life it ſelf, to Chriſt, who became poor, and deſpiſed in the worlds eye, that we though his poverty might be dignified in the Spirit, and made rich in Faith, in grace, in humility, and goodneſs? this is to be heavenly rich in God, in love.</p>
            <p>O who would not leave all, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chrſt for his treaſures of wiſdom and knowledg, and all good things which he gives to his cloſe followers? <hi>This was one word which was ſpoken to me alſo: Loveſt thou me more then theſe; more then Gold, Silver, Lands, Livings, any relations, Golden gifts and Graces, men or meanes? and love not the world, nor the things of it: love nothing, I ſay,</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:170255:27"/> 
               <hi>equall or above me: for he or ſhe that loves any thing more then me, is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of me: ſet not thy affections on things below, on earthly, ſenſitive things; but on Heavenly things above, inviſible glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. If riches encreaſe, ſet not thy heart upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Deare brother was ſuch riches to me, that if I could have but enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his life, and him ſpiritually reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a comfortable ſtate in this life, according to my earneſt and conſtant ſouls deſire, and the deſire of many precious Saints; that our God might have been more glorifyed in his life on earth; O what riches, what a portion of great joy would this have been to my ſoul, none knows: but now ſeeing by this, uncertainty and emptyneſs in all things below the Lord, I am forced to ſay, What is riches, or the encreaſe or ſweet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of any creature-comforts, to the lifting up of Gods lovely counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance upon us! I can ſay now more
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170255:28"/> feelingly, Whom have I in Heaven or in Earth to glory in, or ſtay my ſelf upon, but God alone, from whom flows all our freſh ſprings of comfort, joy, life, love, and ſweetneſs? The Lord, I hope, by our late chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, will make us more holy, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, thankfull and fruitfull in every good work of God; and cauſe the ſword not onely to pierce into our ſouls, but even to divide and ſever more between ſoul and body, fleſh and ſpirit, Chriſt and the Creature; <hi>That nothing may remaine in us, but what loves, admires, and bleſſes our God alone above all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, this is all my deſire, to know more, and do, and patiently ſubmit to the holy will of our Dear God in all things; and to have more ſingle affections to him, and his naked glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p>Chriſtian friend, I have written in theſe papers ſome poor ſtamerings, or what the Lord hath communicated to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170255:28"/> me with comfort in weakneſs, through which I have written this to you, that you with me may bleſs the Lord for his precious loving kindneſs to his unworthy hand-maid. I cannot tell whether I may be troubleſom to you, becauſe ſo tedious at one time. When I begin to write to a Chriſtian friend in this kind, I am always much enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; the more, becauſe but ſlow of ſpeech. In theſe few lines you may perceive a little, that <hi>many are the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the Righteous,</hi> and alſo that the Righteous Lord ſupports ſweetly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them all; and in his own beſt time graciouſly delivering them out of all. Theſe troubles of ours may well be compared to waters, even a flood of waters, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid, that hath wave upon wave: which though it be our Fathers pleaſure, and our portion to wade thorow; yet this is our comfort, VVe ſhall not ſink in them: they may pierce our body, but cannot run
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170255:29"/> thorow our ſouls, to the deſtroying of our life which is hid with Chriſt in God, who is our Head, which ſhall never periſh: and you know that member can never fear drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whoſe head is ſtill above water. Whilſt <hi>Peters</hi> Faith was anchored in Chriſt the Rock of his Salvation, the water to ſence did ſo far give back, that they miraculouſly became a ſolid path to lead him to his Lord: ſo I hope our late, as well as former troubles will tend to lead us neerer to our deſired haven of reſt: for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, all the waters of affliction are to thoſe whoſe faith is exerciſed in their God, but a ſhort Compendious way to Communion and fellowſhip with the Father and the Son in the Spirit, which is beſt of all; better then life, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid; who had, as we have, freſh troubles often, and freſh mercies; freſh Temptations, and freſh deliverances: what ſaid good <hi>David,</hi> when he had deviated
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170255:29"/> and gone aſtray like a loſt ſheep? <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was afflicted I went astray; but now have I kept thy Word.</hi> Here he ſweetly acknowledges tribulations to be meſſengers ſent from God, to lead him to the Shepherd of his ſoul: ſaid he, <hi>Now have I kept thy word:</hi> now do I know by this thy ſanctified viſitation, of a truth, that I am thine: before, I was a loſt ſheep of the houſe of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> All our afflictions, inward and outward, in our ſelves or in the world, 'twill appear to be onely but the corrections of an indulgent Father, for our profit, in the end; to make us rich in God, though poor in our ſelves. In the mean time, the good Lord endue us with Power from on High, whereby we may poſſeſs our ſouls with Patience, till the time of refreſhing from on High ſhall Viſit us; till he who changes times and ſeaſons, changes hearts and conditions with us. <hi>Truly if the Poor Creature could change, or any ways</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:170255:30"/> 
               <hi>help it ſelf, or have any reliefe or help from any broken reed, or ciſterne, beſides the Lord the living Fountain: how would it do, as Iſrael of old did, run from God to them, adoring it ſelf, and Idoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing the creature, men and means, more then admiring the Lord in them, above them?</hi> Truly our natures are too apt to this: for let the Lord but open a little of himſelf to us in any thing or way, we are Readyer to be taken with it then him; <hi>like ſome, who looke more at the Diſh, then the Meate in it.</hi> How apt (let experience ſpeake) are we to take up our reſt in ſomething below our reſt, and not look up high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to the Fountain from whence all our freſh ſprings of comfort floweth? therefore our God ſeeing this not good for us, in wiſdom and love <hi>dries up all Cisternes</hi> and <hi>Pools</hi> when it's <hi>thus with us,</hi> that nothing we run to the creature for in need, may yeild us ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, below himſelf; leſt We ſhould rob him of his glory, and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170255:30"/> give it to ſomething below himſelf, which is not worthy of our heart-love: and his jealouſie is ſuch, that he will not give his glory to another, nor his praiſe to any thing or Idol, but himſelf. To this end therefore he imbitters every thing in the world to us, to wean us from her ſhadowy delights; like loving mothers, who wean their children from the breſt, which is ſo ſweet and dear to them: even thus (as I may ſay) doth God our loving Father with his beloved chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, make every thing vile to them, that he alone may be the preciouſneſs of his Saints, and all things nothing in compariſon, that he alone may be their All in all, above all; their onely boaſt and glory.</p>
            <p>Before this glorious diſcovery of love, I was like another creature, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning like <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, from Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to Hill, and Hill to Mountain; from men to meanes, from means to men: I was, like the Spouſe, reſtleſs in
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170255:31"/> my ſpirit; which made me to ſend my ſpiritual ſenſes all abroad to ſeek Chriſt, as I thought; but truely I found him not in any thing or place, ſave in denying me that ſoul-comfort which I ſought for: all my ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was like <hi>Maries at the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre, forſaking all things for him, as I thought; whom if I could but have found, in my way and time, I ſhould have thought I had found enough;</hi> being led forth to ſeek <hi>The true God in an Ignorant way; being blinded with Ignorance;</hi> I asked every thing below him, ſenſitive things: I asked the Earth, the Sea, and the great Deeps, and the Windy Aire, with the Dwellers therein; alſo the Sun, Moon, and Stars, leſſer and greater; knowing and unknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing creatures; and I found they all anſwered me with one voyce, <hi>We be not thy God; ſeek him, O ſeeker, above us:</hi> Thou art but deceived in us; we are onely by him made and upheld; he is Lord over us: this was without.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170255:31"/> Then I went home, and ſaid to all that were about the doors of my fleſh, Tell ye, my familiars, what ye know of God; O tell me ſomewhat of him whom my ſoul longeth after: and they cryed out alſo to me, <hi>We be not thy God;</hi> it's he hath made us, not we our ſelves. Notwithſtanding all theſe denyals, being ſoul-reſtleſs ſtill, I asked further, even the whole world in general, if it were not my Saviour, and could deliver me from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of corruption; and it anſwered me very powerfully, <hi>I am not,</hi> but I am by him: he whom thou ſeekeſt for in me, even he made me: above me muſt thou ſeek to him that made me, and ruleth all things, to new make thee.</p>
            <p>Being, as you may perceive, Sir, a wandering bird, and ſoul-diſquieted within me, I ſought to every Idol which I made an Idol below the true God for ſoul-reſt, peace of conſcience and joy in the Holy Ghoſt: but like
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170255:32"/> 
               <hi>Noahs</hi> dove, found this not in any thing to refreſh my weary ſoul. Now I finde, that though every thing be beautiful in its ſeaſon, place and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; yet in this reſpect it muſt deny it ſelf, and be nothing, as it did to me; and acknowledg this is not to be had in any created glory on this ſide the Creator himſelf. Every thing ſpoke the ſame to me in this; We be not the Lord thou lookeſt for; but from him, and by him, for his glory. I have found the Apoſtles words true, that many times we may underſtand him by his viſible works in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world.</p>
            <p>In my former Creaturely ſeeking of the Lord, as I have a little menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, I found a vaſt emptyneſs in all things: but when God was pleaſed to ſhew me this, he turn'd me to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and then gave me reſt and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in his love, which is better then life; whereby my hungry thirſty ſpirituall ſtarved ſoul was ſatisfied
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170255:32"/> with that fulneſs <hi>that fills empty no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things with good things.</hi> O it's the ſweet incomes of this Divine fulneſs that makes <hi>The dry land a Pool, and our thirsty lands ſprings of Water.</hi> O when the Lord ſhall thus appear to us, ſhewing us by his light the vileneſs and vanity of every thing which is Excellent within or without us; then indeed the ſoul crys out, <hi>What have I to do any more with Idols,</hi> to ſeek after <hi>Bethel,</hi> after any thing that will not profit; but the <hi>True, Living, Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall God,</hi> who <hi>dwells in everlasting, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utterable, and unſearchable light and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> without beginning or end? True<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when we ſeek the true God aright, we ſhall finde him to be a certain <hi>Light above all Lights,</hi> which no car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal eye can comprehend; and a certain <hi>Voyce</hi> which none in their creaturely ſtate can conceive of: and ſuch a ſweet perfume is Chriſt, which no noſe of ſenſe can attain unto: He is a certain <hi>Sweetneſs above all Sweetneſs;</hi> no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170255:33"/> Ointments, Spices, Milk, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or Manna, is comparable to this ſweetneſs, though ever ſo deſirable; for this is incomparable, above and beyond all, for raviſhing, pleaſant, and ſatisfying: and ſuch an imbrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is Chriſt, our ſoul lover, which no ſenſitive feeling can take hold of; this pure light of life ſhineth where no place is to hold it; and the Voice of Chriſt ſoundeth free where no aire is to help it; and his ſweet ſavour yeildeth ſweetneſs and life where there is no feeding on crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-comforts; and Chriſts imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing is ſuch an imbracing, where no armes are ever pluck'd aſunder.</p>
            <p>Now when the poor ſoul hath thus found and enjoyed <hi>Chriſt in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most Holy Places</hi> of its new heart, whom it ſo earneſtly ſought for, and now entirely loveth; now it cries out, None, none but Chriſt: it now makes account of nothing in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of him, in whoſe favour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170255:33"/> its life: this is it a ſoul ſeeks when it ſeeks God; this is it we love and deſire, Even a manifeſtation of that Jeſus love who hath ſaved us from our ſins, and is <hi>Emanuel,</hi> God with us, in all our troubles, ſorrows, tryalls, and temptations; This bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed man Chriſt Jeſus is our joy and Crown of rejoycing; which cauſeth us to break forth into ſongs of praiſes and Hallelujahs; glory for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more to our God. Finding all things dead, and empty to me, when I ſought Chriſt ſorrowing as I have mentioned; I was afterwards com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted in ſome meaſure, being made willing to wait in ſilence; in which ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence my ſoul with <hi>Hannah</hi> poured out my complaint to him, whom I know when all failes us, doth help us; being mighty to ſave, keep and deliver, even then: for the Lord never leaves his in trouble, but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports and delivers out in his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed time. He that ſets our faces to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170255:34"/> Zion, will undoubtedly bring us hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his own time, to poſſeſs our prepared manſions of glory in his kingdom, to live there in praiſing him to all eternity; ſinging continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally form our God to our God, whom we have been ſeeking, like the Spouſe, abroad, <hi>When he was at home in the ſecret cloſet of the heart; to which when we return in peace, we here finde him in our ſouls by his Spirit, ſitting as onely Lord and King in his Throne, ruling o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the Powers of darkneſs in us.</hi> O for ever happy are they whom God is thus nigh unto in all things; fill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them with all joy in himſelf, through believing: O can any ſoul that hath or doth taſte or enjoy but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo little of the Lord, ſay his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations are ſmall, but very great, and precious; full of life, love, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, like himſelf; and full of vertue and ſtreaming ſweetneſs, like <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans</hi> hony, which revives the droop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirits of ſad hearts, in their dry,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170255:34"/> barren, ſad, ſolitary wilderneſs-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition? Though this is the Fathers will, to have us paſs thorow this ſtate in ſuch harſh and difficult ways to the eye of ſenſe and reaſon, which would much terrifie and perplex a carnal heart; yet our God hath ſuch ſweetneſs to mingle with them, which makes them very paſſable to his Beloved, whom he leads thorow: for the bondage of <hi>Egypt,</hi> he can make tolerable; and the wilderneſs, with all the intricacies thereof, he can make eaſie; who makes rough places a plain way for us to go thorow our Journeys end: <hi>Canaan</hi> alſo, with the high walls and ſtrong enemies there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, even the children of <hi>Anak,</hi> whoſe very ſight ſtruck terror; even theſe our God did and doth make <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querable to his Chriſt, and anointed ones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt by his death hath made his people Conquerors over all enemies, and oppoſitions; by his death he
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170255:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:170255:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:170255:36"/> hath brought to light life, ſtrength, joy, glory, and immortality: though he was, as we are oftentimes, put to death in the fleſh; yet he was quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſpirit: it's this Spirit alone that ſatisfies, quiets, and compoſeth a poor troubled ſoul, when none nor nothing can: and it's this holy Spirits work to lead us out of one truth into another, out of one diſpenſation into a higher; and at laſt poſſeſs us of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect reſt and happineſs: out of which reſt I have been much bewildered and perplexed in my ſpirit, from the ſenſe of a dead loſt condition, not knowing what to do, or which way to turn my ſelf for comfort. About four years ago, I was very ſick and weak; in which weakneſs the enemy took advantage to ſhew his power, and ſet upon me ſtrongly, tempting and troubling me, by raiſing new feares and doubts in my heart; which cauſed me to conclude that all form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er diſcoveries of love which the Lord
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170255:36"/> had communicated to me, was but lying vanities, and deluſions: this trouble was beyond all my former childiſh troubles; for my old life was not ſo much captivated, as my new one, my ſpirit: and truely this temptation lay with ſome confidence upon me, that I knew not what to ſay, or do: I thought ſure the ſmoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing flax, that little ſpark of grace was now extinguiſhed wholly: but I can through rich mercy ſay, Bleſſed and for ever praiſed be Jehovah, who hath ſo ſweetly unboſomed himſelf, and unboweled his precious love to his unworthy hand-maid; telling me, that all my creaturely mutability ſhould not, nor could not alter his unchangable love: for whom he loved once, he loved for ever, to the end, and in the end, endleſs, ever; out of ſin into grace, and out of grace into glory: neither ſhould any of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which I had caſt upon the ſmoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing flax, quench it, by diſowning and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170255:37"/> doubting of the realitie of my ſtate, and the truth of thoſe precious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances I had enjoyed from the Lord: this ſmoaking flax, was God beginning a good work in my ſoul, who would perfect it for his praiſe. O how ſtrongly doth the renewings of the Lords love to us, engage our hearts to honour him all our days, in righteouſneſs and holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs! who notwithſtanding all our unworthyneſs, and greatneſs of ſins, ſins after converſion, as well as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; ſins often reapeated, as well as once onely committed; yet is our loving friend, who loveth us free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, faithfully and conſtant, even in the height of our unconſtancy to him; as he vvas pleaſed to ſhevv me, by not leaving me deſtitute of his mercy and his Truth, in my ſad ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rovvs.</p>
            <p>By this firy conteſt, I finde, that vvhat is of God ſhall and vvill ſtand, all vvindes and vveather, againſt all
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170255:37"/> the many tempeſts and violent ſtormes of all principalities and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of ſpirituall wickedneſs in High places; all this hath been in vain: for this fire, though a little while it did but <hi>Smoak; Yet it will Blaze,</hi> and that with fervent heat: it will never go out; <hi>it's God Everlaſting;</hi> it's God beginning a good work in the ſoul, who will undoubtedly perfect it; it's God in darkneſs, or glimmerings, who will be a Shining light to us, and <hi>fulneſs of Heavens Glory in us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Precious friend, I finde, all that a poor ſoul can do againſt the ſmoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing flax, or <hi>Day-breaking of God,</hi> ſhall never prevail againſt it, for it over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes all, and can be overcome of nothing. O that I could more praiſe and exalt the Lord for his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable loving kindneſs to me; whoſe compaſſions fail not to his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ſervant, though once and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſhe thought they had, under her
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170255:38"/> ſpirits captivity. Now I can through mercy ſay, That Jehovah the infinite and glorious being, ſhews wonders to the dead, and makes the deſolate ariſe out of the grave of ſin and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, as <hi>Lazarus</hi> did, and praiſe him who preaches loving kindneſs to ſuch; and puts an end to death and deſtruction, by his own life and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: I finde the Lord makes known his faithfulneſs and loving kindneſs <hi>in the land of forgetfulneſs,</hi> to ſouls that know not him, nor his wonders in the deeps; which cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me to wait with joy for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manifeſtations of the goodneſs and glory of God: Our God of love, whoſe communications of love are very precious to our ſoules, ſtrongly engaging our hearts to praiſe him: O when, ſays my ſoul, ſhall we do this ſufficiently! When we confeſs God to be his own praiſe. Some ſay of Parents, That their Children can never render to them their due:
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170255:38"/> I am ſure we may ſay ſo of God our Father, and <hi>Wiſdom our Mother, which is Chriſt:</hi> for let a ſoul give never ſo much to God, it comes ſhort of what is his due from us, for making us free, and joyfull in himſelf, from the bondage of corruption, by awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ariſing from under the black dark veils of Ignorance and Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leife; ſaving us from our enemies which are too ſtrong for us; and ſo redeeming and gathering us to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who can no ways be happy out of him.</p>
            <p>Now that we may be made thus happy, Chriſt is a Refiners fire to us, to burn and deſtroy all our droſs, hay, and ſtubble; that we may be made a meet and fit habitation for God through the Spirit. O how ſhould we be content with this purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fire, knowing it to be our Gods deſign of love, in ſending his boſom-Son to utterly aboliſh Mortality, and all that hath Death in it, and then
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170255:39"/> cloath us with life, glory, and Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, according to his will; that we may be fit Brides for the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the Lambe; appearing like thoſe who are begotten of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall ſeed, and ſo changed from glory to glory by love; <hi>Whoſe irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diant beames, and ſweet ſhinings forth, makes the Lion a Lambe, the vile preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ravening ones meek and lovely.</hi> Theſe experienced ſouls, I finde, can more admire, then ſpeak forth the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding riches of Gods grace and free-love, and of his ſtrange and mighty acts in renew making of us, by deſtroying the old creation in us, and transfiguring his new one in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. When this new life and glory, or new creation, is come down into us, or we taken up into it; then may a Chriſtian be called <hi>A new Jeruſalem, a heaven, and earth, wherein dwells righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, or the righteous Lord, who makes all things new, and glorious;</hi> by whoſe in dwelling preſence in our hearts,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170255:39"/> we come to ſee what all the miſts and fogs of darkneſs were, which hindred the Revelation of Chriſt in the Goſpel, and his ſweet diſcoveries of love from us; which was onely our proud, vile, vain, corrupt <hi>ſelf;</hi> this is the obſcuring veile; which veile for our comfort the Lord Jeſus puts aſide, as he ſaid he would do, in the appointed time: this veile of darkneſs I finde alſo to be that vile woman which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of: her ſpecious pretences to man in his loſt condition, to bewitch us from the true knowledg of our dear God and his ways, and ſpirituall Worſhip: but he who is our wiſdom and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, our all, is ſtronger then all enemies, to ſave and keep us for ever from them. Chriſt is our over-topping Mountain, in and by whom God hath promiſed to deſtroy the veile of the covering of the fleſh, ſin, or ſelf-righteouſneſs, which is caſt over all people: this our ſpirituall eyes
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170255:40"/> ſhall ſee with joyfull heart, when Chriſt ſhall be eſtabliſhed above all other Mountains in the ſouls of his people; above every high thought &amp; proud vain imagination, which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to exalt it ſelf above God, where it ought not to be, in our hearts; till the Holy Child Jeſus is born and brought forth thence, our beloved <hi>Iſaac,</hi> heir of all things, with the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life and Peace upon his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to rule all, as only Lord and King, King of <hi>Salem,</hi> Prince of Peace; who hath, doth, <hi>and will bring all things in us into Obedience to his Holy Scepter;</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven our corrupt averſe wills, to ſubject to his Holy Divine will in all things: this great work Chriſt accompliſhes by <hi>degrees,</hi> when he <hi>takes up</hi> his <hi>abode in</hi> our <hi>hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ah what a joy to the ſpirit, but what a ſorrow to the fleſh, is this indwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling preſence in the hearts of his ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified ones! it's a ſorrow to the fleſh or old man in us, becauſe it's death;
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170255:40"/> and it's very joyous to the new man or ſecond creation, becauſe the life and glory of it: the indwelling pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt is a death to all that is evil in us, and a Quickning ſpirit to that which is good: the firſt work our King Jeſus doth when he enters into our hearts; he ſhews us the falſneſs, foulneſs, Ignorance, and darkneſs, and all manner of evil in them; and afterwards he ſhews us the reality and purity of his own native beauty, and Supernaturall Glory. When the Sun of righteouſneſs ariſes in our dark hearts, we then immediately ſee the groſs darkneſs in us; and are then able to diſcerne aright between dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and light, good and evil, truth and Error, by the Spirit of God which ſearches all things, even the deeps of Gods Counſels, and the deeps of our hearts: ſhewing us the weakneſs and unworthyneſs of our ſelves, and alſo the Power, Glory, and Omnipotence of God above them, who can turn
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170255:41"/> and change them how and when he pleaſeth, for his own glory and our ſole comfort; and make us, of vile, precious and beautyful, through his comelineſs. O what could God do more for his vineyard, his people, then he hath done? he hath inveſted them with his own glorious Image, and married them to Himſelf, or Son, which is all one, who is Heire of all things, King of Kings; and alſo dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified them with the graces of his Spirit, and cloathed them with the <hi>Gliſtering Spangles of his Holyneſs, the Angels Glory;</hi> and cull and chuſe them from the common part of Gods earth, to be the chiefe or precious part of his earth: his choice <hi>Golden Mine,</hi> his peculiar treaſure.</p>
            <p>O may we not ſay, who have but ſeen, heard, or taſted ever ſo little a glimpſe of this free rich grace, and precious love of God; what, O what ſhall we render unto the Lord for theſe unſpeakable ſpecial mercies! for
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170255:41"/> certainly God looks for ſome returne of his own from us; he looks for ſome thing preſent from us, as we do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and future from him. He looks we ſhould live anſwerable to our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments and hopes. Says <hi>Peter,</hi> What manner of perſons ought we profeſſors to be in practice, in all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly converſation! O how excellent a thing is it to ſee all the Saints adorne the Goſpell of Chriſt in walking, as well as talking! <hi>Noah</hi> is recorded for a walker with God: O to walk holy as Chriſt did, when he was upon earth in the days of his fleſh, is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent: we know his life was a life of Sanctity, an holy life; for, ſaid he, <hi>Which of you convinceth me of ſin?</hi> and he <hi>who had no ſin nor guile found in his mouth:</hi> nay more, the Devil confeſt him <hi>the Holy one of God.</hi> O what a precious life was this holy life! as Chriſt walked holy, ſo humble: O that all Saints might walk in humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as their Lord and Head did; who
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170255:42"/> though he were Lord and Heir of all, yet he waſhed his Diſciples feet; and humbled himſelf to death, even the death of the croſs. <hi>The humble ſoul looks likest Christ; humility is the veile of Chriſts Bride:</hi> O how beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full doth ſhe look in Chriſts eye, when this <hi>veile of Rebekkah is upon her!</hi> be ye cloathed with humility, ſaith God, to us. As this veile <hi>hides anothers faults, ſo its own graces, as Rebekkah did her beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> true grace, you know, ſhines moſt irradiant through the mask of humility. O what are all Chriſtian duties, without heavenly humility! <hi>Incenſe ſmels moſt ſweet when beaten ſmall;</hi> then it ſends forth its fragrant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume. As Divine humility ſtudies Gods goodneſs, ſo its own unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: <hi>Better is that ſin which thorowly humbles the ſoul, like David, then that duty which lifts up Phariſee-like.</hi> In this the grace of humility is precious; it gives all to God; as <hi>Joab</hi> when he had gotten the Victory, ſent for King
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170255:42"/> 
               <hi>David</hi> to carry away <hi>the Crown of it;</hi> ſo a believer, when he or ſhe hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Victory over ſome corruption or temptation, then they ſet the Crown upon Chriſts head, and ſay with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, By my God I have leaped over a Wall:</hi> and if they finde ſtrength to go tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row duties, then they with <hi>Paul</hi> write Chriſt and free grace upon all: <hi>I la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured more a bundantly then them all: yet not I, but the grace of God in me.</hi> To walk in love and amity, as Chriſt did, to the glory of God, is very deſirea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: he breathed forth nothing but love; he was full of this perfume; as his perſon was lovely, ſo was his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; he was compoſed all of love: he was ſo full of love within, that it broke forth without: <hi>his lips dropped honey, his hands Myrrhe, his ſides blood, his heart Love: love!</hi> O how ought all Saints, who look for glorious things, to come to live in love, as Chriſt did upon earth! O that this ſweet ſpice might ſend out its fragrant ſmell
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170255:43"/> more among Chriſtians, that all things by them might be done in love! <hi>We know,</hi> ſaith <hi>John,</hi> we who live in love and amity, <hi>That we are paſſed from death to life:</hi> ſurely none can love the Perſon of Chriſt really, but they will love his Picture, though very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible to the world. O how might the Saints highly honor God, if they were more united in love, and quite diſpoſſeſſed of theſe two evil ſpirits, that of <hi>ſelf-conceitedneſs</hi> or <hi>vain glory, and uncharitableneſs!</hi> O why ſhould this be? why ſhould not we love as brethren? have we not all one Father? indeed that is a bleſſed ſtrife, when the Saints contend for the faith; this conſiſts in unity. O it's good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, when ſimply out of love, the Saints ſhall be willing to ſuffer pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently for Chriſt, as he did, with a Lamb-like ſpirit: conſidering all our many and great ſufferings are but one dram to his.</p>
            <p>To think of Chriſts ſufferings, and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170255:43"/> of his faithfull ones, <hi>Davids, Jobs, Jeremiahs, Sions,</hi> and many others, that we are not alone in troubles, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, and ſufferings, hath adminiſtred much comfort to me, under all our ſad changes. The Lord give us to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and ſubſcribe more to our Gods will in all troubles, and changes, that we may ſwim in the laver of his Love: Glorifying Him in the fires.</p>
            <p>Sir, having theſe ſcattered Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations upon my ſpirit at preſent, I was moved to communicate them to you by way of writing, being depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of another oportunity. I hope you will accept my poor mite out of my ſcanty ſtore, into you full trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, with love, as I have done yours formerly in your lines. I remember a ſaying of yours which ſtirred me up a little to this communicating: you ſaid, <hi>As the rich ones of the World Viſit one another, opening their treaſures to each other; ſo much more ſhould the Saints de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:170255:44"/> 
               <hi>the goodneſs of God to each other.</hi> Fearing my many lines at preſent may weary you, and being ſomewhat weak in body through ſharp exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, I ſhall now leave you, with all Saints, in the Everlaſting imbraces of our dear Lord Jeſus, whoſe delight is to make his beloved the boſom of his reſt, the bed of Spices; whoſe <hi>precious graces doth perfume all our tribulations:</hi> thorow which we enter into the Kingdom: and this love of the Lord alſo makes the world, and evil of it, a ſweet ſavour of good, Peace, and reſt to us in the end. The good Lord cauſe us more to indulge and honor the ſpirit of theſe graces above them, for the ſweet incomes of them; this will demonſtrate to the world, that <hi>We injoy more Within, then we make ſound of Without; which my ſpirit covets after;</hi> and live not onely in the form, but in the Power of Godlineſs; and ſo can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be led away with the Error of the wicked, or fall from our own ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170255:44"/> but grow in grace, and in the pure, perfect knowledge of our dear God alone. Now the God of love and peace be with ye, making ye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in every good work of faith and love; working in you, and all Saints, and us, that which is well pleaſing in his ſight, cauſing us all to walk as <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels among Men, as the Powers and glory of Heaven upon Earth, like the children of the day in practice,</hi> as burning and ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning lights in this dark world. As the Saints believing heart, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted ſpirit is their glory before God; ſo is their <hi>unſpotted life, their holy walking, their Glory before men;</hi> for when they ſee their good work, they will glorifie their God. Sir, having no further freedom to write more to you now, I ſhall take leave, and reſt, Remaining</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your engaged friend to love and ſerve you, as a member of Chriſt, an heire of Heaven,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170255:45"/> and one anointed of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, SARAH WIGHT, An empty nothing, whoſe fulneſs is all in that Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that filleth all in all.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>I am unskilled in Apologies and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent expreſſions; and if I were not, I had not whereof to glory of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of mans wiſdom.</p>
               <p>Sir, my dear mother is ſtill toſſed with many tempeſts of temptations; but the Lord graciouſly ſupports her, and gives her a little hopes ſometimes of a gracious Iſſue. The Lord caſt her into your heart to beg patience for her, to wait ſilently for a freſh manifeſtation of the Lords love to her ſad ſoul; that ſhe may with joyfull lips ſet forth his praiſe: ſhe ſees ſo much evil in her, and no good, which makes her often doubt whether it will
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170255:45"/> go well with her in the end: and I tell her this is a token for good; for the more vile in our own eyes, the more precious in the ſight of the Lord: <hi>this is a terrible ſight to fleſh and blood, To ſee our ſelves as we are, and God as he is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir, your kind acceptance of my former lines, encouraged me to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent theſe to your view at your ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in ſpare hours.</p>
               <p>Sir, I deſire you to give my cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al reſpects to Mr. <hi>T.</hi> though unknown by face, with thanks for his Chriſtian care and love to us in an unthought-of way: it's not he, but the Lord in him and by him, who will not leave a cup of cold water unrewarded, to him, and you, and all his.</p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
